I'm here to offer you a new way to think about my field,
أنا هنا لأقدِّم لكم أسلوبًا جديدًا للتفكير في مجالي،
artificial intelligence.
الذكاء الاصطناعي.
I think the purpose of AI
أعتقد أن الهدف من الذكاء الاصطناعي
is to empower humans with machine intelligence.
هو تمكين البشر بذكاء الماكينات.
And as machines get smarter,
وكلما تزداد الماكينات ذكاءً،
we get smarter.
نزداد نحن ذكاءً.
I call this "humanistic AI" --
أنا أسمِّي هذا "الذكاء الاصطناعي الآدمي" --
artificial intelligence designed to meet human needs
ذكاء اصطناعي مصمم لتوفير الاحتياجات الإنسانية
by collaborating and augmenting people.
من خلال تجميع وتمكين الناس.
Now, today I'm happy to see
واليوم، أنا سعيد لأرى
that the idea of an intelligent assistant
أن فكرة المساعد الذكي
is mainstream.
أصبحت رائجة.
It's the well-accepted metaphor for the interface between humans and AI.
وهي المتعارف عليه المقبول للواسطة بين الإنسان والذكاء الاصطناعي.
And the one I helped create is called Siri.
والمساعد الذكي الذي شاركت أنا في ابتكاره اسمه "سيري".
You know Siri.
تعرفون سيري.
Siri is the thing that knows your intent
سيري الذي يعلم نواياكم
and helps you do it for you,
ويساعدكم في تنفيذها،
helps you get things done.
يساعدكم في إنجاز مهامكم.
But what you might not know is that we designed Siri
ولكن الذي لا تعلمونه هو أننا صممنا سيري
as humanistic AI,
كذكاء اصطناعي آدمي،
to augment people with a conversational interface
لمساعدة البشر من خلال وسيط تحادثي
that made it possible for them to use mobile computing,
لتمكينهم من استخدام الحوسبة المتنقلة،
regardless of who they were and their abilities.
بغض النظر عن هوياتهم وقدراتهم.
Now for most of us,
وبالنسبة لأغلبنا،
the impact of this technology
تأثير هذه التكنولوجيا
is to make things a little bit easier to use.
هو تسهيل استخدام الأشياء إلى حدٍ ما.
But for my friend Daniel,
ولكن بالنسبة لصديقي دانيال،
the impact of the AI in these systems is a life changer.
تأثير الذكاء الاصطناعي على تلك الأنظمة هو نقطة تحول.
You see, Daniel is a really social guy,
دانيال رجل اجتماعي،
and he's blind and quadriplegic,
وهو أعمي ومصاب بالشلل،
which makes it hard to use those devices that we all take for granted.
ولذلك من الصعب أن يستخدم تلك الأجهزة التي تعتبر بالنسبة لنا أساسية.
The last time I was at his house, his brother said,
وفي زيارتي الأخيرة له، قال أخوه،
"Hang on a second, Daniel's not ready.
"انتظر، دانيال غير مستعد إنه يتحدث
He's on the phone with a woman he met online."
إلى امرأة تعرف عليها من خلال الإنترنت."
I'm like, "That's cool, how'd he do it?"
فقلت، "هذا رائع، ولكن كيف فعل ذلك؟"
Well, Daniel uses Siri to manage his own social life --
في الواقع، دانيال يستخدم سيري لإدارة حياته الاجتماعية --
his email, text and phone --
البريد الإلكتروني، الرسائل والهاتف --
without depending on his caregivers.
بدون الاعتماد علي مقدمي الرعاية له.
This is kind of interesting, right?
أليس ذلك شيئًا مثيرًا للإعجاب؟
The irony here is great.
المفارقة هنا كبيرة.
Here's the man whose relationship with AI
ذلك رجل علاقته بالذكاء الاصطناعي
helps him have relationships with genuine human beings.
تساعده علي الحصول على علاقات مع أشخاص حقيقيين.
And this is humanistic AI.
وهذا هو الذكاء الاصطناعي الآدمي.
Another example with life-changing consequences
مثال آخر للنتائج المؤثرة علي حياة أشخاص
is diagnosing cancer.
هي تشخيص السرطان.
When a doctor suspects cancer,
عندما يشتبه طبيب في وجود سرطان،
they take a sample and send it to a pathologist,
يأخذ عينة ويرسلها إلى أخصائي علم الأمراض،
who looks at it under a microscope.
والذي يراها من خلال مجهر.
Now, pathologists look at hundreds of slides
ينظر الأخصائيون إلى مئات من الشرائح
and millions of cells every day.
وملايين من الخلايا يوميًّا.
So to support this task,
فلدعم تلك المهمة،
some researchers made an AI classifier.
ابتدع بعض الباحثون مصنفًا يعتمد على الذكاء الاصطناعي.
Now, the classifier says, "Is this cancer or is this not cancer?"
ويستطيع هذا المُصنِف تحديد إذا كان ذلك السرطان أم لا
looking at the pictures.
من خلال النظر في الصور.
The classifier was pretty good,
كان المصنف جيدًا جدًّا،
but not as good as the person,
ولكن ليس بجودة الشخص،
who got it right most of the time.
الذي يحصل على نتيجة صحيحة معظم الوقت.
But when they combine the ability of the machine and the human together,
ولكن عندما جمعت قدرة الجهاز مع قدرة الإنسان،
accuracy went to 99.5 percent.
وصل مستوى الدقة إلى 99.5 في المائة.
Adding that AI to a partnership eliminated 85 percent of the errors
إضافة ذلك الذكاء الاصطناعي قضت على 85 في المائة من الأخطاء
that the human pathologist would have made working alone.
التي كان قد يفعلها الأخصائي عند عمله منفردًا.
That's a lot of cancer that would have otherwise gone untreated.
تلك حالات كثيرة من السرطان التي كان من الممكن ألا يتم علاجها.
Now, for the curious, it turns out
ولمحب الإطلاع، لقد اتضح
that the human was better at rejecting false positives,
أن الإنسان كان أنجح في اكتشاف ورفض الحالات السلبية،
and the machine was better at recognizing those hard-to-spot cases.
وكان الجهاز أنجح في اكتشاف الحالات التي يصعب تحديدها.
But the lesson here isn't about which agent is better
ولكن العبرة هنا ليست بخصوص من كان أكثر نجاحًا
at this image-classification task.
في مهمة تصنيف الصور.
Those things are changing every day.
تلك الأشياء تتغير كل يوم.
The lesson here
العبرة هنا
is that by combining the abilities of the human and machine,
هي أن الجمع ما بين قدرات الإنسان والجهاز،
it created a partnership that had superhuman performance.
خلق شراكة ذات أداء خارق لقدرات البشر.
And that is humanistic AI.
وذلك هو الذكاء الاصطناعي الآدمي.
Now let's look at another example
والآن لنرى مثالًا آخرًا
with turbocharging performance.
لأداء خارق.
This is design.
هذا تصميم.
Now, let's say you're an engineer.
فلنقل أنك مهندس.
You want to design a new frame for a drone.
تريد أن تصمم إطارًا جديدًا لطائرة.
You get out your favorite software tools, CAD tools,
تستعين بأدوات برامجك المفضلة، وأدوات CAD،
and you enter the form and the materials, and then you analyze performance.
وتدخل الشكل والمواد، ثم تحلل الأداء.
That gives you one design.
ذلك يأتي لك بتصميم واحد.
If you give those same tools to an AI,
إذا أعطيت نفس الأدوات للذكاء الاصطناعي،
it can generate thousands of designs.
يستطيع أن ينتج لك آلاف التصاميم.
This video by Autodesk is amazing.
هذا الفيديو ل "Autodesk" مذهل.
This is real stuff.
هذه حقيقية.
So this transforms how we do design.
ذلك يغير طريقة عمل التصاميم.
The human engineer now
الآن يحدد المهندس البشري
says what the design should achieve,
ما الذي يجب على التصميم تحقيقه،
and the machine says,
ويقوم الجهاز،
"Here's the possibilities."
بعرض الخيارات.
Now in her job, the engineer's job
الآن في وظيفتها، وظيفة المهندس
is to pick the one that best meets the goals of the design,
هي تحديد الاختيار الأمثل الذي يحقق الهدف من التصميم،
which she knows as a human better than anyone else,
والذي تعلمه هي كإنسانة أفضل من أي شيء آخر،
using human judgment and expertise.
من خلال الحكم البشري والخبرة.
In this case, the winning form
في هذه الحالة، النموذج الفائز
looks kind of like something nature would have designed,
يبدو كشيء من تصميم الطبيعة،
minus a few million years of evolution
ناقص بضعة ملايين سنة من التطور
and all that unnecessary fur.
وكل هذا الفراء الذي لا لزوم له.
Now let's see where this idea of humanistic AI might lead us
والآن لنرى ما قد تقودنا إليه فكرة الذكاء الاصطناعي الآدمي
if we follow it into the speculative beyond.
إن اتبعناها إلى فكر أبعد من ذلك.
What's a kind of augmentation that we would all like to have?
ما هو نوع التطور الذي نود جميعًا أن نحصل عليه؟
Well, how about cognitive enhancement?
ما رأيكم في تقوية حاسة الإدراك؟
Instead of asking,
بدلًا من أن نسأل،
"How smart can we make our machines?"
"إلى أى مدى نستطيع أن نجعل الأجهزة ذكية؟"
let's ask
لنسأل
"How smart can our machines make us?"
"إلى أي مدى تستطيع الأجهزة أن تجعلنا أذكياء؟"
I mean, take memory for example.
أعني، لنتخذ الذاكرة كمثال.
Memory is the foundation of human intelligence.
الذاكرة هي أساس الذكاء البشري.
But human memory is famously flawed.
ولكن الذاكرة البشرية ليست مثالية.
We're great at telling stories,
نحن ماهرون في سرد القصص،
but not getting the details right.
ولكن بدون التفاصيل الصحيحة.
And our memories -- they decay over time.
وذاكراتنا -- تضمحل مع مرور الوقت.
I mean, like, where did the '60s go, and can I go there, too?
أعني، إلى أين ذهبت الستينيات، وهل يمكن أن أذهب هناك أيضًا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But what if you could have a memory that was as good as computer memory,
ولكن ماذا لو تستطيع الحصول على ذاكرة قوية كذاكرة الكُمبيوتر،
and was about your life?
وتكون متعلقة بحياتك؟
What if you could remember every person you ever met,
ماذا لو تستطيع أن تتذكر كل شخص قابلته من قبل،
how to pronounce their name,
كيفية نطق اسمه،
their family details, their favorite sports,
تفاصيل عن عائلاتهم، رياضاتهم المفضلة،
the last conversation you had with them?
آخر محادثة تمت بينكم؟
If you had this memory all your life,
لو كانت لديك تلك الذاكرة طوال حياتك،
you could have the AI look at all the interactions
ممكن أن تكون لديك نظرة الذكاء الاصطناعي في كل تعاملاتك
you had with people over time
مع الناس على مرور الوقت
and help you reflect on the long arc of your relationships.
وتساعدك على التفكير في جزء من دائرة علاقاتك.
What if you could have the AI read everything you've ever read
ماذا لو كان من الممكن أن تجعل الذكاء الاصطناعي يقرأ كل ما قرأته أنت
and listen to every song you've ever heard?
ويستمع إلى كل الأغاني التي استمعت أنت إليها؟
From the tiniest clue, it could help you retrieve
من أصغر إشارة، ممكن أن يساعدك في استرجاع
anything you've ever seen or heard before.
أي شيء قد رأيته أو سمعته من قبل.
Imagine what that would do for the ability to make new connections
تخيل ماذا ممكن أن تفعل من أجل القدرة على إجراء اتصالات جديدة
and form new ideas.
وتكوين أفكار جديدة.
And what about our bodies?
وماذا عن أجسادنا؟
What if we could remember the consequences of every food we eat,
ماذا لو كان في استطاعتنا أن نتذكر تأثير كل طعام تناولناه،
every pill we take,
وكل حبة دواء أخذناها،
every all-nighter we pull?
كل سهرة طويلة قمنا بها؟
We could do our own science on our own data
يمكننا أن نصنع العلوم الخاصة بنا من بياناتنا الخاصة
about what makes us feel good and stay healthy.
عما يجعلنا نشعر شعور جيد ونبقى أصحاء.
And imagine how this could revolutionize
وتخيل كيف يمكن لذلك أن يحدث ثورة
the way we manage allergies and chronic disease.
في كيفية التعامل مع الحساسية والأمراض المزمنة.
I believe that AI will make personal memory enhancement a reality.
أعتقد أن الذكاء الاصطناعي سوف يجعل تقوية الذاكرة الشخصية حقيقة.
I can't say when or what form factors are involved,
لا أستطيع أن أقول متى أو ما هي العوامل المشاركة،
but I think it's inevitable,
ولكن أعتقد أنه أمر لا مفر منه،
because the very things that make AI successful today --
لأن العوامل التي تجعل الذكاء الاصطناعي ناجحًا اليوم --
the availability of comprehensive data
توافر بيانات شاملة
and the ability for machines to make sense of that data --
وقدرة الماكينات على فهم تلك البيانات --
can be applied to the data of our lives.
من الممكن أن يتم تطبيقها على البيانات الخاصة بحياتنا.
And those data are here today, available for all of us,
وحاليًّا تلك البيانات متاحة لنا جميعًا،
because we lead digitally mediated lives,
لأننا نعيش حياة معروضة على وسائل الإعلام،
in mobile and online.
على الهاتف وعلى الإنترنت.
In my view, a personal memory is a private memory.
من وجهة نظري، الذاكرة الشخصية هي ذاكرة خاصة.
We get to choose what is and is not recalled and retained.
يكون لنا حرية اختيار ما يمكن أن يسترجع وأن يحفظ.
It's absolutely essential that this be kept very secure.
إنه من الضروري أن تبقى تلك البيانات آمنة جدًّا.
Now for most of us,
بالنسبة لمعظمنا،
the impact of augmented personal memory
تأثير تلك الذاكرة الشخصية المدعمة
will be a more improved mental gain,
سوف يكون تطور ذهني،
maybe, hopefully, a bit more social grace.
وربما، نأمل ذلك، فضيلة اجتماعية.
But for the millions who suffer from Alzheimer's and dementia,
ولكن بالنسبة إلى الملايين الذين يعانون من مرض الزهايمر والخرف،
the difference that augmented memory could make
الفارق الذي تستطيع الذاكرة المطورة أن تحدثه
is a difference between a life of isolation
هو فارق ما بين حياة العزلة
and a life of dignity and connection.
وحياة الكرامة والاتصال.
We are in the middle of a renaissance in artificial intelligence right now.
نحن الآن في منتصف عصر نهضة الذكاء الاصطناعي.
I mean, in just the past few years,
أعني، إنه في السنوات القليلة الماضية،
we're beginning to see solutions to AI problems
بدأنا نرى حلولًا لمشاكل الذكاء الاصطناعي
that we have struggled with literally for decades:
كنا قد عانينا منها على مر العقود:
speech understanding, text understanding,
فهم الكلام، فهم النص،
image understanding.
فهم الصور.
We have a choice in how we use this powerful technology.
لدينا حق اختيار كيفية استخدام تلك التكنولوجيا الجبارة.
We can choose to use AI to automate and compete with us,
يمكننا استخدام الذكاء الاصطناعي للتنافس معنا،
or we can use AI to augment and collaborate with us,
أو نختار أن نستخدمها للتطوير والتعاون معنا،
to overcome our cognitive limitations
للتغلب على القيود المعرفية لدينا
and to help us do what we want to do,
ولتساعدنا على تحقيق أهدافنا،
only better.
وأكثر من ذلك.
And as we discover new ways to give machines intelligence,
وبينما نحن نكتشف طرقًا جديدة لتزويد الماكينات بالذكاء،
we can distribute that intelligence
يمكن لنا القيام بتوزيع ذلك الذكاء
to all of the AI assistants in the world,
على جميع أجهزة الذكاء الاصطناعي المساعدة،
and therefore to every person, regardless of circumstance.
وبالتالي على كل شخص، بغض النظر عن الظروف.
And that is why,
ولذلك،
every time a machine gets smarter,
كلما ازداد ذكاء الماكينة،
we get smarter.
ازداد ذكاؤنا.
That is an AI worth spreading.
هذا نوع من الذكاء الاصطناعي يستحق الإنتشار.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)